A Guide to the Taconic Foundation records FA407
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Board Materials, 1958-2013; 2; 7.44 Cubic Feet 20 document boxes (including 4 clamshell boxes and 1 half-box); 68 Megabytes 479 digital files
  - Meetings, 1973-1991
    - Special Meeting, 1988 June 16 (Box 185, Folder 1807)
      File consists of resolution and power of attorney for purchase of property formerly belonging to Ruth H. Foy in Danby, VT.
    - Meeting Materials, 1988 June (Box 185, Folder 1808)
    - Meeting Materials, 1988 October (Box 185, Folder 1809)
    - Memoranda, 1988 (Box 186, Folder 1810)
      This file includes two letters acknowledging donations to the Schomburg Center and to the Municipal Reference and Research Center of the City of New York, in October 1988. The letters were added to this file in processing.
    - Memoranda, 1988 (Box 186, Folder 1810 A)
    - Memoranda, 1988 September-October (Box 186, Folder 1811)
      File labeled "LKG [Lloyd K. Garrison] Board Materials 10/25/88: Hold." The file includes some memoranda not found in the other 1988 board files, along with many duplicates.
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1989 January (Box 186, Folder 1812)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1989 June (Box 186, Folder 1813)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1989 October (Box 186, Folder 1814)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1989 December (Box 186, Folder 1815)
      Materials include a Report to the Taconic Foundation on Past Efforts and Future Prospects in Youth Employment, November 1989, focusing particularly on the Smokey House project.
    - Memoranda, 1989 (Box 186, Folder 1816)
    - Memoranda, 1989 July (Box 186, Folder 1817)
      File contains report on the Evolution of Taconic's Grantmaking Policies, compiled from policy review memos dating from 1978 to February 1986. Report marked: "For Mr. Doyle and Mr. Mister."
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1990 April (Box 186, Folder 1818)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1990 June (Box 186, Folder 1819)
      File includes a June 1991 report on a survey of former participants in the Smokey House program.
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1990 October (Box 186, Folder 1820)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1990 December (Box 187, Folder 1821)
    - Memoranda, 1990 (Box 187, Folder 1822)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1991 February (Box 187, Folder 1823)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1991 June (Box 187, Folder 1824)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1991 October (Box 187, Folder 1825)
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1991 December (Box 187, Folder 1826)
    - Memoranda, 1991 (Box 187, Folder 1827)
      Correspondence and memoranda addressed to the Board of Directors concerning meeting dates and discussions.
  - Meetings, 1997-2012; 65.4 Megabytes 409 digital files
    The 1997–2012 Meetings files combine material from three sets of paper files, plus a set of electronic records.
    The overlapping sets of paper files require some explanation. For the period May 1998–April 2006, there were two sets of board meeting files, which we have integrated in processing. One series appears to have been Lisa Philp's files (starting in September 1998), as it includes her notes and marginal notations. The other set may have been a more general office file, but it also contains meeting notes by Monica Neal (who kept the minutes). In addition to the board packets and memos, this series also contains various financial and statistical reports. This set of files, which we attribute to Monica Neal, ends with the April 2006 meeting (Monica Neal left J.P. Morgan and the Taconic Foundation in the summer of 2006).
    There was also a third set of board meeting files, for the period 1997–2004. These files appear to have been a set of office files, housed in ring binders, and possibly maintained by Hildy Simmons, though a few files include materials with notations by Monica Neal. For the most part this series contained unmarked copies of board meeting materials and memoranda, all of which duplicated material in the other files. Unique items (e.g., check request letters, copies of minutes) and or items with notations have been removed and integrated with the combined set of board materials.
    In integrating these three sets of files, we have tried to maintain some distinction between materials from the separate sets of files, even as we have generally discarded duplicate materials. In most cases, we have used Lisa Philp's files as the base set of files, because they cover the broadest time range, and we have added the materials from Monica Neal's files to them, using a blank sheet of paper to separate the two sections. We have generally not noted the small amount of material added from the third set of files.
    There is only one set of board files for the period September 2006–2009. These materials were filed with and continue Lisa Philp's set of files; they consist mainly of the meeting booklets, with very few notations.
    Materials from 2010–2012 are from Casey Burgess Casteneda's files, but they include some notations by Lisa Philp, who served through May 2011.
    As far as possible digital and analog files have been integrated in their arrangement and description. Electronic Meetings Materials from May 2009 to December 2012 and various Meeting Notes for 2003–2007 are integrated in the Meeting Materials and Notes files. Because the digital board files tend to be sorted by document type, we have retained this arrangement for the Agendas, Dockets, and Memos.
    - Agendas, 1998-2012; 1.1 Megabytes 47 digital files
    - Dockets, 1998-2011; 5.9 Megabytes 43 digital files
    - Meeting Materials and Notes, 1997-2012; 54.8 Megabytes 222 digital files
      Files include board meeting booklets, supplemental materials, memoranda, and minutes, as well as notes and marginalia. Monica Neal served as meeting secretary from 1998 to April 2006.
      Files for 2006–2009 consist primarily of the meeting booklets, with very few notes. Megan Watkins, Eve Rodsky, and Sara Rosen served as meeting secretaries during this period.
      Materials for 2010–2012 appear to be from Casey Burgess's files. They include some interleaved material, highlighting, and marginal notes. Casey Burgess Casteneda served as meeting secretary from 2010 to 2013.
      - 1997 (Box 187, Folder 1828)
        Meeting materials for the January 9, 1997 board meeting are found in the file Organizational Records: Transition to J. P. Morgan: Board Meetings.
        Meeting materials for May, September, and December board meetings. Also includes check request letters for 1997. This file may have been maintained by Hildy Simmons.
      - 1998 May (Box 187, Folder 1829)
      - 1998 September-October (Box 188, Folder 1830)
        The board was originally scheduled to meet in September.
      - 1998 December (Box 188, Folder 1831)
      - 1999 May (Box 188, Folder 1832)
      - 1999 September (Box 188, Folder 1833)
      - 1999 December (Box 188, Folder 1834)
      - 2000 May (Box 188, Folder 1835)
      - 2000 September (Box 188, Folder 1836)
      - 2000 December (Box 188, Folder 1837)
      - 2001 May (Box 189, Folder 1838)
      - 2001 September - October (Box 189, Folder 1839)
        Materials consist only of docket packet. The meeting, scheduled for September 11, did not take place.
      - 2001 December (Box 189, Folder 1840)
      - 2002 May 7 (Box 189, Folder 1841)
      - 2002 July 17 and August 8 (Box 189, Folder 1842)
        The board met by telephone conference call for each of these meetings. There appear to have been no board booklets prepared for the meetings.
      - 2002 September (Box 189, Folder 1843)
      - 2002 December (Box 189, Folder 1844)
      - 2003 February 27 and April 2 (Box 189, Folder 1845)
        These two meetings were conducted via telephone conference call. There appear to have been no board booklets prepared for the meetings.
      - 2003 May (Box 189, Folder 1846)
      - 2003 September, 43 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 190, Folder 1847)
      - 2003 September (Box 190, Folder 1847 A)
      - 2003 December, 42 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 190, Folder 1848)
      - 2004 May (Box 190, Folder 1849)
      - 2004 September (Box 190, Folder 1850)
      - 2004 November, 107 Kilobytes 2 digital files (Box 190, Folder 1851)
      - 2005 March, 53 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 190, Folder 1852)
      - 2005 May, 47 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 190, Folder 1853)
      - 2005 September (Box 190, Folder 1854)
      - 2005 December (Box 190, Folder 1855)
      - 2006 April, 201 Kilobytes 4 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1856)
      - 2006 September, 47 Kilobytes 1 digital file (Box 191, Folder 1857)
      - 2006 November, 84 Kilobytes 2 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1858)
      - 2007 May and December, 95 Kilobytes 2 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1859)
      - 2008 May (Box 191, Folder 1860)
      - 2008 September and December (Box 191, Folder 1861)
      - 2009 March and May, 1 Megabytes 6 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1862)
      - 2009 December, 402.5 Kilobytes 7 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1863)
      - 2010 May, 7.2 Megabytes 5 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1864)
      - 2010 September, 1.8 Megabytes 22 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1865)
      - 2010 December, 1.5 Megabytes 17 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1866)
      - 2011 March, 18.2 Megabytes 33 digital files (Box 191, Folder 1867)
      - 2011 May, 2.6 Megabytes 15 digital files (Box 192, Folder 1868)
      - 2011 September - October, 4.9 Megabytes 22 digital files (Box 192, Folder 1869)
      - 2011 December, 4.5 Megabytes 23 digital files (Box 192, Folder 1870)
      - 2012, 12 Megabytes 55 digital files (Box 192, Folder 1871)
        File includes some financial records which are restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2033.
      - 2012 (Box 192, Folder 1871 A)
        Confidential material separated from folder 1871. Restricted for twenty years from date of creation - open in 2033.
    - Memos, 3.6 Megabytes 98 digital files
      - General, 1998-2007; 2.3 Megabytes 65 digital files
        File includes memos arranged chronologically and related to board discussions, plus more general memos on topics such as localization strategies, urban boarding schools, and Brookings Institution education research.
      - Cover Memos for Briefing Books, 1999-2010; 1.1 Megabytes 26 digital files
      - Bill Green Memorial, 2002-2005; 222 Kilobytes 7 digital files
- Organization Records, 1959-2012; 3; 7.2 Cubic Feet 14 document boxes, 2 card files, 1 oversized flat box; 51.4 Megabytes 325 digital files
  The Organization Records series contains materials relating to the Currier Family, the history and administration of the Taconic Foundation, and the Taconic Foundation trustees.
  There are few or no personal records for Stephen and Audrey Currier. Apart from a few files relating to the Currier children, the Currier Family files mainly concern memorial arrangements for Stephen and Audrey Currier following their disappearance in January 1967. The Memorial Book files include reminiscences of the Curriers gathered from friends and associates, and these tributes provide additional detail on the Curriers. There is one file of addresses Stephen Currier gave in 1966–1967 as president of Urban America. A card file recording the Curriers' personal giving from 1958 to 1967 is another significant source, and it should provide some insight into the distinctions and overlap between the Curriers' personal philanthropy and that of the Taconic Foundation particularly in its early years.
  The Organization Records series mainly documents the Foundation's history and administration. It includes a second card file (Grants Index), which records Taconic Foundation grantmaking from 1958 to around 1997. For Taconic's main grantees, the cards provide a detailed summary of their grant history. The cards also provide useful access to grant information in cases where grant files are lacking or there are variant names.
  Documents include reviews and reflective reports on the Foundation's past and future directions. Several files (including many of the Grantmaking files) reflect efforts to compile source material for a planned history of the Taconic Foundation. A significant proportion of the material pertains to the Foundation's transition to management by J.P. Morgan in 1997, and its efforts in the mid- to late-1990s to define its future course and then to accomplish its final spend down in the period 2008 – 2013.The Research by Staff files contain a series of position papers and program reviews, mostly created in 1998–1999. Research supported by Taconic includes papers on affordable housing coops by Susan Saegert, New Markets Tax Credits by P. Jefferson Armistead, and a 1989 evaluation of youth employment programs by Marc Freedman. Files relating to the Smokey House Project in Danby, Vermont, are found in this series rather than in the Grants series, reflecting, perhaps, its unique connection to the Foundation. Administrative files consist primarily of various financial records.
  The files relating to the Trustees are uneven and provide only limited documentation of their work with the Foundation. There are sustained correspondence files for some trustees, such as Susan Curnan or Lloyd Garrison, but in most cases the Trustees files present only a partial and often insignificant record.
  - General, 2000-2010; 6.5 Megabytes 16 digital files
    File contains various materials relating to Taconic Foundation investments and program directions. Includes material on the Poverty and Race Research Action Council, Pratt Institute Center, Smokey House, and the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board, as well as reports on Out-of-School-Time programs. File was originally labeled "Miscellaneous."
    File includes some confidential material that is restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2028.
  - General Correspondence, 2000-2005; 640 Kilobytes 28 digital files
    File contains correspondence from Taconic Foundation staff to various trustees and some general materials concerning grants administration. File originally named "Letters."
  - Center for Summer Learning, 2005, 2010; 2.5 Megabytes 4 digital files
    File concerns Summer Learning Gap and proposal from Johns Hopkins University to provide resources relating to summer learning.
  - Contracts
    - Owens, Christine, 2002-2003; 84.5 Kilobytes 4 digital files
      File concerns payments for research on urban boarding schools.
    - Saegert, Susan, 2002-2003; 334.5 Kilobytes 7 digital files
      Records relate to consultancy agreement with Susan Saegert to survey the literature on Limited Equity Housing Cooperatives.
  - Currier Family
    - Currier, Andrea, 1980-1985, 1993 (Box 193, Folder 1872)
    - Currier, Andrea and Lavinia, 1977 (Box 193, Folder 1873)
    - Currier, Lavinia, 1981-1994 (Box 193, Folder 1874)
    - Currier, Michael, 1981-1991 (Box 193, Folder 1875)
    - Currier, Stephen R.: Remarks, 1966-1967 (Box 193, Folder 1876)
      File consists of addresses Stephen Currier gave as president of Urban America.
    - Currier, Stephen R. and Audrey Bruce
      - Condolence Letters, 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1877)
        Letters of condolence on the Curriers' disappearance. The file contains original letters, most of which were addressed to Jane Lee Eddy. The unlabeled folder was marked "on table." Photocopies of some of these letters are found within the Memorial Book file in folder 1880.
      - Memorial Book, 1967
        The file contains correspondence and reminiscences concerning the Curriers collected for inclusion in a memorial book.
        - 1967-1968 (Box 193, Folder 1878)
        - 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1879)
        - 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1880)
          This file contains photocopies of correspondence and letters of sympathy, addressed mainly to Jane Lee Eddy, on the loss of the Curriers.
      - Memorial Programs
        Materials mainly concern suggested memorial projects, but also include articles on the Curriers and the program from their Memorial Service.
        - 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1881)
        - 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1882)
      - Memorial Service, 1967
        File concerns planning and arrangements for the February 15, 1967, Memorial Service.
        - 1967 (Box 193, Folder 1883)
        - 1967 (Box 194, Folder 1884)
      - Personal Giving (Card Index), 1958-1967 (Box 207)
        Card file, arranged alphabetically by recipient, recording the Curriers' personal contributions and support to various organizations. Cards record contact information, dates and amounts given (in cash or securities), and in the case of performances frequently the nature and title of the event. File includes cards for the Curriers' giving to the Taconic Foundation.
        The Grants Index, which documents Taconic Foundation grants, also includes some references to personal contributions by the Curriers.
    - Patterson, Don, 1982 (Box 194, Folder 1885)
      Andrea Currier married Donald W. Patterson Jr. in November 1980.
  - Currier House (Radcliffe College), 1970-1971, 1976 (Box 194, Folder 1886)
    Dedication of Audrey Bruce Currier House, November 18, 1970. Includes John Simon's remarks on the occasion.
  - Currier Memorial Scholarship Fund
    The Audrey and Stephen Currier Memorial Scholarship Fund supported a program at Harvard and Radcliffe College of scholarship assistance for minority or disadvantaged students.
    - Correspondence
      In most cases, envelopes have been discarded in processing.
      Contributions and acknowledgments. Radcliffe College acknowledged its receipt of the funds from the Taconic Foundation in 1970.
      - (A-F), 1967-1968 (Box 194, Folder 1887)
      - (G-O), 1967 (Box 194, Folder 1888)
      - (P-Z), 1967-1968 (Box 194, Folder 1889)
      - 1970 (Box 194, Folder 1890)
    - List of Contributors, 1967 (Box 194, Folder 1891)
      File originally contained photocopies of all checks received. These copies have not been retained.
  - Finances and Investments
    - Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette, Inc., 1968-1971 (Box 194, Folder 1892)
      Concerns endowment conferences and Taconic Foundation investments.
    - Financial Statements, 1991-1994 (Box 194, Folder 1893)
      Taconic Foundation Financial Statements, audited by Edward Isaacs & Company.
    - Investments (Excerpts from Board Minutes), 1998-2003 (Box 194, Folder 1894)
    - Ledger, 1958 May 15 - 1965 December 31 (Box 206)
      Taconic Foundation Inc. General Ledger.
    - Montag and Caldwell, Inc., 1981-1984 (Box 194, Folder 1895)
      Correspondence with investment firm concerning decision to consolidate Taconic Foundation portfolio.
    - Partnership (Legal Entity), 1980 (Box 194, Folder 1896)
      File contains Private Placement Memorandum by Institutional Partners, L.P., June 30, 1980, and addendum.
    - Performance Statements, 2004-2005 (Box 194, Folder 1897)
      J. P. Morgan statements to Taconic Foundation trustees concerning account performance.
  - Gautreaux v. Romney, 1970-1971 (Box 195, Folder 1898)
    Suit targeted racially discriminatory practices in Chicago public housing system.
  - Grantmaking and Foundation History
    - Grants Index (Card File), 1958 - circa 1997 (Box 208)
      Card file, arranged alphabetically by name of grantee. Cards record contact information and calendar grant actions, signficant correspondence, and in some cases meetings and reports.
    - Fiftieth Anniversary, 2008, 2010; 1.4 Megabytes 5 digital files
    - Funding History, 1984 (Box 195, Folder 1899)
      Alphabetical list of grants, 1958-1984.
    - Funding History, 1970-1993 (Box 195, Folder 1900)
      Annual statements of grants paid, broken down by category. Not every year is represented.
    - Grant Letters, 1996-1997 (Box 195, Folder 1901)
      File contains copies of grant award notices for 1996, sorted alphabetically by program area: Housing and Community Development, Programs Related to Youth Employment, Other Programs to Serve Youth, Programs to Promote Equality of Opportunity, and Field of Philanthropy.
      The file also includes copies of award letters for grants voted in late 1996 and announced in January 1997; this set may not be complete.
    - Grantmaking Policies, 1989 (Box 195, Folder 1902)
      Memo on "Evolution of Taconic's Grantmaking Policies" (1970s-1986).
    - Grants Guidelines, 2005-2010; 401 Kilobytes 8 digital files
    - Grants Lists, 1992-1997, 2002-2012; 587 Kilobytes 11 digital files (Box 195, Folder 1903)
      Annual lists of grants paid, sorted by program areas, starting in 1995. Data for 1992-1996 are compiled in a single list.
      File contains both paper and digital records. Starting with 2002, lists are in digital format.
    - Grant Summary, 1998-2009; 333 Kilobytes 15 digital files
      Summaries of annual grant spending by program area, beginning with 1996.
    - Historical Board Memos and Guidelines, 1965-2004 (Box 195, Folder 1904)
      File contains policy reviews of Taconic in the 1970s and 1980s, and 1997 memo on Gatekeeping. Later materials consist of board correspondence.
    - Historical Grant Data, 1990-2009 (Box 195, Folder 1905)
      File contains copies of annual reports, check stubs, and charts of grants by funding areas. Material was compiled for use in preparing a fiftieth-anniversary report.
    - Historical Grant Data (Check Stubs), 1990-1997 (Box 195, Folder 1906)
      Check stubs, removed from ring binder, record grant payments made from May 2, 1990 to March 10, 1997.
    - Taconic Foundation Evaluation, 1964 (Box 195, Folder 1907)
      Memos on program and policy direction.
    - Taconic Foundation in the Seventies, 1978 (Box 195, Folder 1908)
      File includes copy of memo on Taconic Policy Review, June 7, 1978.
    - Taconic History: By-Laws, 1991-2006 (Box 195, Folder 1909)
      File contains copy of undated by-laws and agreement with J. P. Morgan, February 27, 1997. File name retained from the original.
    - Taconic History: Martin Luther King, Jr. Papers Project, 2003, 2005 (Box 195, Folder 1910)
      File consists of two requests from the King Papers project for documents pertaining to King. File name retained from the original.
      At its May 2004 meeting, the Taconic board agreed that it would check to see whether its archives contained materials relevant to the King papers project at Stanford University.
    - Taconic Time Line, 1958-1984 (Box 195, Folder 1911)
      Grantmaking broken down by decade and funding area.
  - Memberships
    - 2000-2003 (Box 196, Folder 1912)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 196, Folder 1913)
  - New York Regional Association of Grantmakers (Affordable Housing Briefing), 1993, 2008 (Box 196, Folder 1914)
    Program presented on April 30, 2008, by the Partnership to Preserve Affordable Housing, and cosponsored by the Independence Community Foundation, Surdna Foundation, and Taconic Foundation.
    One unrelated item from 1993 added to file in processing.
  - Oral History Project (Jan Jaffe), 2012; 5.2 Megabytes 17 digital files (Box 196, Folder 1915)
    Contract to conduct research and oral history interviews concerning Taconic Foundation history, and background materials for that research. The file consists of both paper and digital records. While there may be some duplication of items between the two formats, the digital and analog contents do not necessarily coincide.
    Paper files are from Accession 2013:009, box 93.
    File includes some confidential material that is restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2033.
  - Oral History Project (Jan Jaffe), 2012 (Box 196, Folder 1915 A)
    Confidential material - Restricted for twenty years from date of creation. Open in 2033.
  - Quo Vadimus